Guide to the Henry DeWitt Barnett Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Henry DeWitt Barnett Papers
1917-1982.
[Bulk Dates: 1970-1981]
Barnett, Henry DeWitt, 1917-
13.5 linear ft (ca. 16,000 items in 35 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0077
4078939
This collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, reports, documents, notes, clippings, and other printed materials of Henry DeWitt Barnett, a missionary in China.
Biographical Note
Missionary in China, religious official. Barnett was a Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA) executive in New York from 1946 until 1965. From 1965 until 1971 he served as Quaker International Affairs Representative for East Asia with the American Friends Service Committee, based in Tokyo. From 1971 until 1982 he has been a consultant in Hong Kong to the Department of East Asia and the Pacific of the Division of Overseas Ministries of the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ) in developing a U.S.-China people-to-people program.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, reports, documents, notes, clippings, and other printed materials of Barnett. The files contain correspondence with missionaries, journalists, and organizations promoting Chinese-American relations, memoranda, periodicals, reports of travelers in China, and other related materials. While there are some earlier materials, these files deal mostly with the period from 1970 to 1981. Also, correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts, reports, documents and printed materials, mainly about China, the Barnett family and the Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), 1974-1982.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series:
Series I: Henry DeWitt Barnett Papers, 1917-1981
Series II: Henry DeWitt Barnett Papers, 1984 addition, 1974-1982
Subjects
American Friends Service Committee.--International Affairs Division.; Christian Church (Disciples of Christ).--Division of Overseas Ministries.--Dept. of East Asia and the Pacific.; China--Description and travel.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; Missionaries--China.; Missions--China.
Acquisition
09/--/82 M-82-09
Gift of H. DeWitt Barnett, 1982 & 1984.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Henry DeWitt Barnett Papers, 1917-1981 [Bulk Dates: 1970-1981]
  This series comprises papers and correspondence mostly from the period 1970 to 1981. Material is arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Correspondence & "archives" (family papers, clippings, notebooks, & misc unsorted papers)
    - 1917 - 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971 - 1973 (Box 2)
    - 1973 - 1975 (Box 3)
    - 1975 - 1981 (Box 4)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box 5)
  - American Indians (Box 5)
  - Amnesty International (Box 5)
  - Angell, Charles (Box 5)
  - Asia Monitor (Box 5)
  - Asian-American Consultation (Box 5)
  - ACFOD (Asian Cultural Forum On Development) (Box 6)
  - Barr, Ruth & Betty (Box 6)
  - Book reviews (Box 6)
  - Bread for the World (Box 6)
  - Cambodia (Box 6)
  - Chen, Zeming (Box 6)
  - China
    - (1) (Box 6)
    - (2) - (5) (Box 7-10)
    - (6) (Box 11)
  - Christian Conference of Asia (Box 11)
  - Cuba (Box 11)
  - Division of Overseas Ministries (Disciples of Christ) (Box 11)
  - Ecology (Box 12)
  - Flory, Margaret (Box 12)
  - General Assembly - 1977 (Box 12)
  - Hatem, George (Box 12)
  - Hanegar, Warren & JoAnna (Box 12)
  - Herod, Bill & Peggy (Box 12)
  - Hong Kong
    - (1)-(3) (Box 13-15)
    - (4) (Box 16)
  - Human Rights (Box 16)
  - Hunter, Deirdre & Neale (Box 16)
  - Japan
    - (1) (Box 16)
    - (2) (Box 17)
  - Johnson, E.H. (Box 17)
  - Kampuchea (Box 17)
  - Keh, Yun-i (Box 17)
  - Kloepfer, Warner (Box 17)
  - Korea (Box 17)
  - Leaflets (Box 17)
  - Louvain reflections (Box 17)
  - McGovern campaign (Box 17)
  - MacInnis, Don (Box 17)
  - Mackie, Pat (Box 17)
  - Massay, George E. (Box 17)
  - Meditations (Box 18)
  - Monthly index (Box 18)
  - Nixon & the U.S. (Box 18)
  - Okinawa (Box 18)
  - Oshika, Yasuhiro (Box 18)
  - Peng, Ming-min (Box 18)
  - People-to-People project
    - (1) - (2) (Box 19-20)
    - (3) (Box 21)
  - Philippines (Box 21)
  - Ponsoncuy, Camillia J.N. (Box 21)
  - Quaker International Affairs Representative (Box 21)
  - References from the press (clippings) (Box 22)
  - Revolution by nonviolence (Box 22)
  - Stainton, Michael (Box 22)
  - Stewart, Lucille (Box 22)
  - Student revolution (Box 22)
  - Ta Kung Pao (Box 22)
  - Thailand (Box 22)
  - Theological "Roadshow" (Box 22)
  - Tindera, Mike & Syomara (Box 23)
  - Torture (Box 23)
  - Understanding China newsletters (Box 23)
  - UBCHEA (United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia) (Box 23)
  - U.S. after Nixon (Box 23)
  - Whitehead, Ray & Rhea (Box 23)
  - Whitfield, Elsie (Box 23)
  - Wilson, Paul & Dede (Box 23)
  - Wright, Cliff (Box 23)
  - Zen Buddhism (Box 23)
  - Address books (Box 24)
  - Appointment books (Box 24)
  - Photographs (slides & filmstrip) (Box 24)
  - Tape recordings (Box 25)
- Series II Papers, 1974-1982. (1984 Addition)
  This series comprises an additional gift of papers and correspondence made in 1984. Material is arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Acorn (Box 26)
  - Adams Correspondence (Box 26)
  - Africa (Box 26)
  - Barnett, Andrew & James (Box 26)
  - Barnett, H. Dewitt (notebook) (Box 26)
  - Barnett, Rebecca (speeches) (Box 26)
  - Barnett, Robert (speeches) (Box 26)
  - Barnett Family items (Box 26)
  - Barnett Family (miscellaneous) (Box 26)
  - Barnett Family - U.S. Trip (1982) (Box 26)
  - Booz, Elizabeth B. ("Ben") and Patrick R. ("Paddy") Kunming (Box 26)
  - Canadian Council of Churches (Box 27)
  - China
    - Christians in (1) - (2) (Box 27)
    - Education in (Suzanne Pepper) (Box 27)
    - Housing in (Marcia Goldstein) (Box 27)
    - Letters from (1979- ) (Box 27)
    - Maryknoll Fathers (Box 27)
    - Mental Health in (Box 27)
    - Population (Box 27)
    - Prayer Guide (Box 27)
    - Reference Items
      - (1) (Box 27)
      - (2) - (4) (Box 28)
    - Social Problems (Box 28)
    - Study Project (Box 28)
    - Tour of Friendship (1982) (Box 28)
    - Tour Plans (1981-82) (Box 28)
    - Trip
      - 1977 (Notes) (Box 28)
      - 1977 (Report) (Box 29)
      - 1977 (Reports) (1) - (2) (Box 29)
      - 1978 (1) - (2) (Box 29)
      - 1978 (Notes) (Box 29)
      - 1978 (West) (Box 29)
      - 1980 (Report) (Box 30)
      - 1981 (Box 30)
      - 1982 (Box 30)
    - Visitors (Box 30)
    - Visual Aid Project (Box 30)
    - Chinese Language Study (Box 30)
  - Christian Church
    - "Disciples - Who are they?" (Box 30)
    - Disciples Peace Fellowship (Box 30)
    - D.O.M.
      - Board of Directors (Box 30)
      - Disciples in China (Box 30)
      - Division Council (Box 30)
      - Experiences in an African Setting (Box 30)
      - General Assembly (1981) (Box 31)
      - Guide to Mission around the Globe (Box 31)
      - Information and Recommendations (November 1981) (Box 31)
      - Information and Recommendations (March 1982) (Box 31)
      - Information and Recommendations (June.1982) (Box 31)
      - Overseas Personnel (1981) (Box 31)
      - [General] Principles and Policies (Box 31)
      - Recent News Coverage of South Africa (Box 31)
      - Report on Consultation in Geneva (June 1982) (Box 31)
    - I.C.W.A. (international Christian Women's Association) - Quadrennial Assembly (June 1982) (Box 31)
    - Joint Staff Working Group on International Concerns (1981-82) (Box 31)
    - Peace with Justice (Box 31)
    - Speaking Assignments (DeWitt Barnett)
      - Chapel Talk (7/24/81; 11/6/81; 1/29/82) (Box 32)
      - Boonegrove, Ind. (9/12-13/81) (Box 32)
      - World Outreach, Poseyville, Ind. (11/7-8/81) (Box 32)
      - D. Kagiwada, Crestview, Ind. (11/16/81) (Box 32)
      - Unitarian Church, Hobart, Ind. (10/25/81) (Box 32)
      - Hartford City, Ind. (12/6/81) (Box 32)
      - Frankfort, Ind. (1/31/82) (Box 32)
      - Valparaiso, Ind. (2/14/82) (Box 32)
      - Lebanon, Ind. (2/21/82) (Box 32)
      - Duncan, Oklahoma (2/27-3/8/82) (Box 32)
      - Mitchell, Ind. (3/14/82) (Box 32)
      - North Carolina Region (3/20-29/82) (Box 32)
      - Logansport, Ind. (10-8/82) (Box 32)
      - Indianapolis, Ind. (4/20/82) (Box 32)
      - Flora, Ind. (4/25/82) (Box 32)
      - Charlestown, Ind. (5/2/82) (Box 32)
      - Stillwater, Oklahoma (5/3O-6/6/82) (Box 32)
    - Yearbook and Directory
      - 1981 (Box 32)
      - 1982 (Box 32)
  - Christian-Marxist Work Group (1) - (2) (Box 33)
  - The City in History - Lewis Mumford (Box 33)
  - Crown Life Insurance (Box 33)
  - Easter, Maud and David (Box 33)
  - Elliott, Elsie (Box 33)
  - Fri, Yacht (Box 33)
  - Hersey, John - China Homecoming (Box 33)
  - Hong Kong
    - Holy Carpenter Church (Box 33)
    - Piu Kiu School & Tong Kin-Kwok (Box 34)
  - Indianapolis - International Festival, 1981 (China Booth) (Box 34)
  - Kwong Kong Kit, Rt. Rev. Peter (First Chinese Anglican Bishop) (Box 34)
  - Jyotinekitan Community, Hong Kong (Murray & Mary Rogers) (Box 34)
  - Macau (Box 34)
  - People-to-People
    - Gift Calendar (Christmas 1974) (Box 34)
    - Mailing List (Box 34)
    - Committee Minutes (Box 34)
  - Political Action (Box 34)
  - Printed Material (Box 34)
  - Taiwan
    - General Information (Box 34)
    - Human Rights Violations (Box 34)
  - USCPFA (U.S.-China Peoples Friendship Association) (Box 35)
    - China Tour, 1978 (Box 35)
    - National Convention, Houston, Texas-(1981) (1) - (3) (Box 35)
    - Chapter Talk (5/8/82) (Box 35)
    - Religious Leaders (October-November 1982) (Box 35)
  - U.S.-China Relations - Foreign Policy (Box 35)
  - U.S.-China Understanding (Box 35)
  - Y'smen's Club, Indianapolis (September-November 1981) (Box 35)